<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Faith in the just victorious over the world a sermon preached at the Savoy in the French Church, on Sunday Octob. 10, 1669 / by D. Brevall ... ; translated into English by Dr. Du-Moulin ...</title>
            <title>Foy victorieuse du monde dans les justes. English</title>
            <author>Bréval, Monsieur de (François Durant), d. 1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12498282</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12498282</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62587</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29333)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62587)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 307:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Faith in the just victorious over the world a sermon preached at the Savoy in the French Church, on Sunday Octob. 10, 1669 / by D. Brevall ... ; translated into English by Dr. Du-Moulin ...</title>
                  <title>Foy victorieuse du monde dans les justes. English</title>
                  <author>Bréval, Monsieur de (François Durant), d. 1707.</author>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Peter, 1601-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Nott ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Foy victorieuse du monde dans les justes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62587:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62587:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FAITH IN THE JUST Victorious over the WORLD A SERMON Preached at the SAVOY in the French Church, on Sunday <hi>Octob.</hi> 10. 1669.</p>
            <p>By Dr. BREVALL, heretofore Preacher to the the Queen-Mother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated into Engliſh by Dr.</hi> Du-Moulin, <hi>Canon of</hi> Canterbury.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Nott,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Queens-Arms the <hi>Pell-mell.</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62587:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62587:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou are not obliged to me for the Sermon I give you, becauſe it is a Preſent which I give unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. There are ſo many Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every day that are ſo much better, and are not Printed, as it would have ſeemed to me a Crime, if any thing leſs then Neceſſity had made me do mine that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. I had no other reaſon to excuſe my ſelf to many people that deſired it of me: and I had been firm in this refuſal but for the occaſion I am about to tell.</p>
            <p>The Superiour of the <hi>Capuchins</hi> at <hi>Somerſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe</hi> meeting me in the Street the Sunday after my Sermon, as I went to the <hi>French Church</hi> in the <hi>Savoy</hi> with one of the Elders, ſtopped me moſt uncivilly, and told me I might have been aſhamed to have preached the laſt Sunday ſo many foul, ſo many infamous things; ſo many Crimes and Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, which had ſo horribly ſcandalized all the World.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62587:3"/>
            <p> I confeſs this Language did ſurprize and move me, becauſe till then I had had nothing but Praiſes and Acclamations, as well from the one Partie as the other; yet I only told him he did more wrong to himſelf then to me by ſo unjuſt a reproach, and that he did oblige me to make my Sermon pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, that ſo I might have more Witneſſes and Judges then I had Auditors, though they were as many as the Church could hold.</p>
            <p>But before I did it, I asked counſel of the Wiſeſt, the moſt Vertuous and Illuſtrious Perſons that I could reaſonably conſult with. Their Advice was, that I ought with ſpeed to clear my ſelf publickly from ſo wicked a Calumnie; that ſo by the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood of this, which I ſhould make apparent to all, the Impoſtures of my Enemies in other ill ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that they make of me might be known.</p>
            <p>I obeyed this Counſel, or rather this Order that was given me, without other deſign then to juſtifie my Doctrine. It concerns me not much what they ſay or believe of me; one thing excepted, which I cannot ſuffer without complaining of my Perſecutors, who durſt ſay, that in the laſt Wars I offered my ſervice to the King of <hi>England</hi> againſt the King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have a good Witneſs to the contrarie, who knows that the paſſion I then expreſſed for this Kingdom was without prejudice to the Loyaltie I owe to that wherein I was born.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62587:3"/>
            <p> To ſhew you in few words the unſinceritie of thoſe people that perſecute me: You muſt know, that ſoon after my Converſion they would have it that I had been a Spie for <hi>England</hi> againſt <hi>France,</hi> to draw upon me the Hatred of the <hi>French</hi> that are here. I give God thanks, who hath always kept me in the Duties I owe to both theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; I look on them both as my Countrie ſince I was born in the one, and prepare my ſelf to die in the other.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs this is more then enough to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all credit from my Enemies in the reſt of the Accuſations, which from time to time they frame againſt me, they are ſo unlikely; and the World is alreadie ſo far diſabuſed, that my Defence is needleſs. Themſelves begin not to dare to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh them ſo boldly, and are almoſt reduced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach me with nothing but my Marriage, and I am verie happie that people who hate me ſo much, have nothing to ſay againſt me but that which is ſo innocent and ſo lawful; would to God they could everie where be reproched with the ſame thing; it might ſave them from other more hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Accuſations. I am ſure the libertie of one Sacrament (as they call it) would hinder the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of many Sacrileges.</p>
            <p>I will take ſome more ſeaſonable time to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain my ſelf further, when I ſhall come to anſwer for mine own Perſon, and not for a Sermon.
<pb facs="tcp:62587:4"/>Beſides, if my Behaviour were ill, my Doctrine may be good for all that; and I defie the preciſeſt Critick, (ſo he be a Chriſtian) to find one word amiſs in it: or if it be true, that I am deceived in any thing, they will do me a pleaſure to rectifie me; for I am of Saint <hi>Augustines</hi> mind, <hi>I may he in an Errour, but I would not be.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:62587:4"/>
            <head>THE PRAYER Before the SERMON.</head>
            <p>LOrd, whoſe MAJESTY covers the Heavens, and whoſe Mercies, the Earth; we come with ſouls full of devotion and humble confidence, to render our duties and implore thy favour; we beg it generally for all men, and particularly for Chriſtians: but more eſpecially for thoſe that worſhip and ſerve thee in the Purity of the Goſpel; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and aſſiſt their Churches where they are in oppreſſion, preſerve and increaſe their ſplendor and tranquillity where they are flouriſhing; principally in theſe Kingdoms of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> O good God! Poure thy choiceſt Bleſſings on the KING, whom thou haſt given them to defend them againſt their enemies; eſtabliſh his Throne more and more, and ſince thou haſt eſtabliſhed him to be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately under thee and thy Chriſt, univerſal Governor in all his Eſtates, and Defender of the Faith: Raiſe his vertue as high as thou haſt raiſed his Glory; Bleſs the Queen his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort; their Royal Highneſs's the Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>York,</hi> with all the Royal Family; the Lords of the Council, the Nobility with all the Orders of the Kingdom. But, O God, pour thy double ſpirit upon their Paſtors, the Arch Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, the Biſhops, and all other Miniſters and Diſpenſers of thy Sacraments, of thy Myſteries, and of thy Word; let them ſuſtain the weight and dignity of their charge with ſuch doctrine, zeal and good life as is requiſite. Thou ſeeſt, O Lord, the need <hi>I</hi> have of this grace for my ſelf; and ſince thou haſt made me by thy mercy, one of the Preachers of thy Goſpel, by the ſame mercy make me worthily to anſwer the end and ſublimity of thy Miniſtry: Enlighten my ſpirit
<pb facs="tcp:62587:5"/>warm my heart, purifie my lips, and generally give me that which thou wilt <hi>I</hi> ſhould diſpenſe to thy people: diſpoſe their minds to profit by my inſtructions, and that they and <hi>I</hi> may go from hence better then we came hither. O Lord, theſe are the mercies that we crave of thee this day; and ſince the acknowledgement of thy benefits never fails to bring new mercies upon us, we praiſe thee, O God, for the infinite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſses of thy bounties to us in general and in particular: chiefly, that thou haſt redeemed us by thy Son, and that thou doſt daily inſtruct us by his Example, and by that of all the Saints which have followed him. O Lord! the thanks we can give are too little, we offer Chriſt himſelf unto thee, for our duties as well as for our ſins; and as it is by him only that we owe thee all things, ſo it is by him alone, that we will or can acquit our ſelves. O Lord, then look on thy Chriſt, and ſeek in him all thou wilt have of us, as we ſeek in him and by him, all that we would have of thee; it is in that frame of heart that we lie proſtrate at thy feet, and ſay unto thee what himſelf hath taught us to ſay,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Our Father which art in Heaven,</l>
               <l>Hallowed be thy Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62587:5"/>
            <head>THE TEXT Is in the Firſt Epiſtle of Saint JOHN, Chap. V. Ver. IV.</head>
            <head type="sub">For whatſoever is born of GOD overcometh the World; and this is the Victory that overcometh the World, even our Faith.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rovidence, which is admirable in all things, is ſo eſpecially in the Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy of the Scripture, where, that which is ſometimes but occaſional, is nevertheleſs of infinite uſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence: which made St. <hi>John Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> ſay ſo well in his Homily on <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>That the Scripture ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſave wiſe and holy Deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this we have in the Text a very Authentick Inſtance, ſince the whole verſe ſeems to have been written only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the occaſion of that which went before, where St. <hi>John</hi> having ſaid, that <hi>the Commandments of God are not grievous;</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62587:6"/>and foreſeeing the objections of an infinite number of people, to whom they are (without doubt) very difficult, found himſelf inſenſibly engaged to render this reaſon; That all which <hi>is born of God overcometh the World,</hi> and that <hi>this is the victory which hath overcome the World, even our faith.</hi> Now you ſee, Chriſtians, that there was nothing more neceſſary to be taught, then that which at firſt ſight ſeem'd to be taught us here by chance only.</p>
            <p>In effect, where can be found in one or the other Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, more inſtruction, or more myſteries then in theſe few words? muſt not one have leaned on the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of JESUS, as this Apoſtle did? muſt not one have drunk (as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks) in this ſource of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to comprehend ſo many marvels in ſo few words? <hi>I</hi> dare ſay, that not only the Law and the Prophets, but that all the Goſpel it ſelf, all its ſpirit, all its perfection, is divinely incloſed in this Text: for, if they are born of God, if they have overcome the world, and if the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph be obtained by faith, which is wanting to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of the vertue, and the accompliſhment of the deſign of Jeſus Chriſt in the ſanctification of men?</p>
            <p>This divine Birth, this illuſtrious triumph, and this victorious faith, being then (as it is evident) the laſt effort of grace, and the moſt glorious work of the Spirit in the ſoul of a Chriſtian; ſhall I not this day competently fulfil the diſpenſation of my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, if in one verſe of Scripture, which <hi>I</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to expound, I clear unto you theſe three great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries that comprehend all holineſs? letting you ſee,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who are thoſe which are born of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What victory they obtain over the World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What this Faith is which makes them obtain this Victory.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62587:6"/>
            <p> Chriſtians! here is all that ſeems to me neceſſary for the explaining of my Text: which ſays plainly, that <hi>Whatſoever is born of God overcometh the world, and that this is the victory which hath overcome the world, even our Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will begin with clearing the firſt part; My Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren! Give ſuch attention as it deſerves; and Thou, O my God, give the bleſſing, which <hi>I</hi> crave.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>THE FIRST PART.</head>
               <p>One of the greateſt Queſtions that ever puzled the Philoſophers before the knowledge of the Goſpel, was; to finde, whether any thing could be born of God, by any ſort of Generation; the greateſt number, and the moſt ſubtil, believed that it was impoſſible; Firſt, (ſaid they) becauſe God is a Spirit, and Spirits in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender not, having no power proper, or appointed for that uſe: Secondly, becauſe he is God, and in that quality he ought neceſſarily to be One; which he ſhould no more be if he were capable of generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; becauſe, a God can beget none but a God, for then he ſhould introduce a multitude contrary to his Eſſence; from whence they concluded in the end, an impoſſibility that any thing ſhould be born or begotten of God. But the Goſpel having better enlightned us by the obſcurities of faith, then the Philoſophers had done by the light of Science; we know infallibly, that this birth or generation is not impoſſible; and this text of <hi>S. John</hi> is enough to teach it; ſince, by ſaying, <hi>All that is born of God overcometh the world,</hi> it ſuppoſeth, either divers perſons or divers things to be born of him; but, the better to diſcern of what this Apoſtle ſpeaks here, we ought to take notice that generally, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture gives this illuſtrious praiſe to be born of God, to all that he hath produced with ſome reſemblance of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: and, it is a doctrine conformable enough to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62587:7"/>which teaches, that all that is born of a principle, receives from it not only being, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance beſides.</p>
               <p>Now, as God doth diverſly communicate the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of himſelf, to the things that he produceth; from thence it comes, that all poſſeſs not by the ſame title the honour to be born of him</p>
               <p>A great man, and one of the moſt learned the world ever had in Philoſophy or Divinity; obſerves ſubtilly and ſolidly five different manners, wherein the things that God hath produced have ſome reſemblance with him:
<note place="margin">Similitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Veſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae.</note> for, this reſemblance (ſaith he) may be, either of Nature, or of Trace, or of Image, or of Grace, or of Glory; whence he concludeth, that the advantage to be born of God, (that is, to have God for Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) belongeth</p>
               <p n="1">1. To the Word.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To Creatures meerly material.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To Creatures Intelligent and Reaſonable.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To the Juſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To the Glorified.</p>
               <p>To the Word by reſemblance, or rather, by Identity of Nature.</p>
               <p>To Creatures meerly material by ſome imperfect traces, or by ſome obſcure marks of the Excellency of God.</p>
               <p>To Creatures intelligent and reaſonable (that is, to Men and Angels) by their underſtanding and reaſon, which are the illuſtrious Images of God himſelf.</p>
               <p>To the Juſt, by communication of grace and holineſs.</p>
               <p>To the Glorified, by the imitation of his Glory.</p>
               <p>Theſe reſemblances that all things have with God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as you ſee) ſo different, make us eaſily conceive, that God is diverſly the Father of them; and that the advantage to be born of him, is more or leſs noble, according as the reſemblance is more or leſs perſect.</p>
               <p>That which is (without compariſon) above all others,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62587:7"/>is the reſemblance of Nature which belongs only to the Verbe; and which belongs not to him ſpecifically, (as Philoſophers and Divines ſpeak) but individually: that is, The <hi>Word</hi> is not only like his Father as we are to ours; having the ſame nature with him; for, ſince it is impoſſible there ſhould be more then one God, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be poſſible that his Nature ſhould multiply: ſo, when the Father produceth his Eſſential Word, he gives him not another Nature like his, but the ſame as his own: from whence it is that the Title of the Son of God (to ſpeak ſtrictly) can belong to none but him: and it is by a metaphor meerly, and a kinde of uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it is attributed to others. The Scripture doth fully witneſs it when it ſays ſo often, <hi>that he is the only Son,</hi> or, <hi>only begotten of God,</hi> and when by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence it ſaith in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.32. That <hi>He is God's own Son;</hi> and when it ſays in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. That <hi>it is to him alone that God bare this witneſs,</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee:</hi> And finally, that in the 110. <hi>Pſal.</hi> it is of none but him that the Father ſpeaks, when he ſays according to the Latin Verſion, <hi>I have begotten thee of my boſome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, we find nothing, either in Divinity or in the Scripture it ſelf; of this great Priviledge, and of this proper and particular Title of the Word, but the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of reſemblance that he hath with his Father, and which other things have not.</p>
               <p>The holy Spirit it ſelf which proceedeth from the Father (as the Goſpel teacheth us) and who hath the ſame nature with him, yet is not called the Son, and it is not ſaid that he is born, nor that he is begotten, becauſe he doth not proceed formally (as Divines teach us) by way of reſemblance, ſince (at the leaſt) as they ſay very rationally, the holy Spirit is the production of Love and not of Knowledge: ſo that proceeding from the Will, and not from the Underſtanding of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it cannot have a formal reſemblance with its principle:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62587:8"/>Philoſophie it ſelf teaching us, that reſemblance is not an effect of the Will, but of the Underſtanding, becauſe it is proper to the Will to carry it ſelf to its Object, whereas the Underſtanding attracts his Object by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing on it his reſemblance. Whence it is, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> ſays, <hi>that the Underſtanding becomes all things;</hi> not by changing it ſelf into them, but, on the contrary, by changing them into it ſelf. Moreover, it is from thence, that the Production or Term of the Will is called a Weight, a Propenſion, an Inclination — which does not at all ſignifie reſemblance; but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the underſtanding is called Verb, Image, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation. Therefore, Scripture never gives theſe Names to the Holy Spirit, but to the Son only; whoſe Name, ſaith St. <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 19. is, <hi>The Word of God.</hi> Now, this word <hi>Verb</hi> ſignifies either the thought, or the word, and we know that the thought is the repreſentation of the object that one thinks of, and the Word is the Image of the thought it ſelf; ſo that, both in the one and in the other ſenſe, the word Verb applied to the Son in the Goſpel is a name of reſemblance.</p>
               <p>But St. <hi>Paul,</hi> willing more clearly to expound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſaith to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> That <hi>he is the Image of God;</hi> and to the <hi>Hebrews, That he is the ſplendor of his Glory, and the figure of his Subſtance,</hi> according to the Latin Verſion; or of his Perſon, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Greek Original.</p>
               <p>Thus, by all theſe reaſons, and ſo many authorities it is properly the ſecond Divine Perſon that is born of God. Yet, it is not of that our Text ſpeaks, when St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>That all which is born of God overcometh the World by Faith;</hi> for, though Jeſus Chriſt, who is this Adorable Perſon, hath overcome the World, as himſelf doth witneſs by the ſame Evangeliſt, in the 16th. <hi>chapter</hi> of his Hiſtory, <hi>verſe</hi> 33. and, though it be alſo in ſome manner by means of faith that he hath triumphed; yet it is not of him that the Text ſpeaks, becauſe it is eaſie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62587:8"/>to comprehend by that which goeth before, and that which cometh after; that, it is of them that have faith, that theſe words ſhould be underſtood: and that they cannot belong to Jeſus Chriſt, who, though <hi>he be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and Finiſher of our Faith,</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls him, in the XIII. <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi>) yet he hath it not formally, ſince he cannot have faith of that which he hath the knowledge, the experience of the ſight.</p>
               <p>So when St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks here of that which is born of God, he ſpeaks but of thoſe which have onely an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect reſemblance of him, differing from that of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet he ſpeaks not of all ſorts: for,</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is clear that by that which is born of God, he means not things meerly material, which have only a Trace or Footſtep of likeneſs to him; it is true, that God having produced them, and they repreſenting to us, (as they do all) ſome of his perfections, God may juſtly be called their Father: <hi>Job</hi> in this ſenſe calleth him <hi>the Father of the rain,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>It is be that hath begotten the dew:</hi> he might ſay as much of all other creatures; though deſtitute of intelligence and reaſon, ſince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that God made them, they have moreover this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, to repreſent him in ſome ſort,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> in the judgment of St. <hi>Paul</hi> who ſaith in the firſt Chapter of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> the 20. verſe, that, <hi>the inviſible things of him are clearly ſeen from the Creation of the world, being underſtood by the things that are made.</hi> But the end of our Text ſhews evidently, that he ſpeaks not of that ſort of creatures, although in ſome reſpects, it may be ſaid they are born of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, neither is it of Angels or Men in the quality of intelligent and reaſonable creatures; for though the Angels are the leaſt imperfect images of God, (which gave occaſion to a learned man to call them, <hi>The bright Looking Glaſſes of the Godhead</hi>) and though by the right of this reſemblance there is nothing in Nature that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62587:9"/>more juſtly deſerves the title of the children of God then they do; and though himſelf by the mouth of <hi>Job</hi> calls them ſo often by this glorious Name: yet it is manifeſt that it is not of them that St. <hi>John</hi> here makes mention, when he ſpeaks of thoſe who are born of God, ſince he ſpeaks of ſuch as are in the world, and have ſought with it, and have triumphed over it by faith, which (you ſee) cannot be applied to Angels: Nor doth he ſpeak of men, conſidered only as reaſonable; for though rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath made them fair Copies, and illuſtrious Images of the Divinity, to anſwer (what St. <hi>Paul</hi> highly in their praiſe ſaith) that <hi>they are the Image of the Glory of God:</hi> and to deſerve that the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> ſhould call God <hi>their Father by the general right of their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation:</hi> yet, it is not of them (at leaſt in the quality of reaſonable creatures only) that the text we expound, ſpeaks, who overcome the world by their faith, and not by all the ſtrength of their reaſon and underſtanding.</p>
               <p>Then, they muſt needs be either the Juſt, or the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified that are here ſpoken of. Doubtleſs, they are not the Glorified; for, though they have this noble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of Glory with God, who doth almoſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them into himſelf, as St. <hi>John</hi> expounds it, in the third of his firſt Epiſtle: and that they are called in the Scripture <hi>Children of God</hi> more properly then all other created things, as it appeareth in <hi>Luke</hi> 20. where they are expreſly called <hi>The Children of God,</hi> becauſe they are children of the Reſurrection, heirs and actual poſſeſſors of Glory; yet, our Text ſpeaks not of them, they being no more at ſtrife with the world, the clear ſight of God having happily taken away their ſai h.</p>
               <p>It remaineth then, that it muſt needs be of the Juſt on earth that our Text ſpeaks, that is, of thoſe that God hath regenerated, who reſemble him in grace and holineſs, ſince there is nothing in this Text, which may not, and ought not rightly, to be applied to them. For,</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62587:9"/>
               <p> Firſt, they are born of God. I prove it by three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Reaſons. The firſt is, that it is impoſſible they ſhould be born of any other: The ſecond, that he deals with them as a Father: And the third, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble him.</p>
               <p>That they cannot be born of any other but God, the Scripture and the Fathers, eſpecially S. <hi>Paul</hi> and S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> are altogether for it, when they ſay ſo often, that Juſtification is the work of God. In effect, Chriſtians! aſſemble all the forces of Men and Angels; aſſemble all Prelates and all Kings; aſſemble all Prieſts and all Popes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they cannot make one juſt with all the Power of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they boaſt ſo much of. I ſay no more then what every good Philoſopher and every ſound Divine ought to agree to; ſince in the very Schools it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Doctrine, that Creation is a work ſo proper to God, that it is impoſſible for all other Powers of Heaven and Earth to create ſo much as one grain of Sand onely; and that neither Man nor Angel can obtain of God that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Judge, my Brethren, from the more to the leſs; what we ſhould think of the work of Juſtification, which is a greater benefit then the Creation of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Worlds: ſince the Creation is but a Paſſage from the nothing of Nature to the being of Nature: and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is a Paſſage from the nothing of Grace to the being of Grace. Now there is without compare a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſtance between Grace and its privation, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Nature and hers: the paſſage then is much more difficult, and the one requires more force then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Why? the whole World coſt God but one word to make it; but there was need of all his bloud onely to juſtifie men, nay, there was need of all his blood to juſtifie one Man onely; for which there is no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but that the dignity of Grace was infinitely higher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that of Nature, becauſe it is a participation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, as <hi>S. Peter</hi> teacheth us whereas Nature is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an effect of his Power: from whence we muſt needs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> if Creation can belong to none but God,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62587:10"/>it is impoſſible that Juſtification ſhould belong to any other. In effect, who can give a participation of the Being of God, but God himſelf? and what but an infinite Agent can be capable of an infinite production? It is known that none but God is ſo; then the juſt are born of God, becauſe it is impoſſible they ſhould be born of any other.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon to perſuade you to this (Brethren) is, that God takes a Fatherly care of them: for where did we ever ſee a Father take ſo much care for his Children, as God takes of the juſt? He brings them up, he feeds them, he protects them, he advanceh them: the whole Scriptuto ſpeaks unto us of no other thing almoſt in both Teſtaments. You read at all times his tenderneſs and goodneſs in their education<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that there is nothing wanting in order to bring them up well; neither Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, nor Promiſes, nor Threatnings, nor Recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor Chaſtiſements; and all for their good: for he intends nothing by ſuch different Diſpenſations but to make them better. If they want any thing for their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual nouriſhment, my Brethren! he not onely imploys his graces and his Vertues, but he imploys himſelf to nouriſh them with his Holy Spirit, and with all that he is, as well as with all that he hath in the Myſteries of our Sacrament. You doubt not of his Protection, ſince he tells us in the Scripture, that <hi>he preſerves them as the Apple of his eye, that he covers them under the ſhadow of his wings, that he doth compaſs them with a wall of fire, that he watches day and night to defend them, that he comforts them in their afflictions, that he upholds them in their proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perities, to the end they may not be caſt down by the one, nor puff't up by the other:</hi> briefly, <hi>he aſſiſts them in all their needs, and declares himſelf an enemy to all their enemies.</hi> What will he not do to advance them? <hi>He makes them go up</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks <hi>from vertue to vertue, from knowledge to knowledge, from holineſs to holineſs, from Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Glory:</hi> we have an admirable expreſſion of it in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62587:10"/>one of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, where he ſhews, that <hi>God from Eternity began the advancement of the Juſt, and ſets it forward more and more to the end of the World; Whom he did foreknow</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he alſo did predeſtinate; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo called, and whom he called them he alſo juſtified, and whom he juſtified them he alſo glorified;</hi> becauſe of their calling he hath ſanctified them, and after their ſanctification he hath glorified them.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians! in earneſt, are not theſe the cares of a Father, and of the beſt of all Fathers?
<note place="margin">Tampius nemo, tam pater ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. Tert.</note> This was it which made <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſay, <hi>There was no Father ſo good, nor ſo much a Father as God:</hi> it is then an evident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration that <hi>the Juſt are born of him,</hi> ſince none take moſt care of ſtrangers.</p>
               <p>But the greateſt and moſt ſenſible argument to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, that they are in effect <hi>born of God,</hi> is, That they reſemble him. For it is the doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt in the 8th. of St. <hi>John;</hi> and of St. <hi>John</hi> himſelf in the third of his firſt Epiſtle; and of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 9th. of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans, That a man is Son to him whom he reſembleth, and of thoſe whoſe works he does: if the works of</hi> Abraham, <hi>he is the Son of</hi> Abraham: <hi>if the works of God he is the ſon of God: if the works of the Devil, he is the ſon of the Devil.</hi> Here you ſee the great characters of the filiation of the Juſt, this is it which doth chiefly eſtabliſh their right, even that their conduct, their life, their works, and all the reſt, is but a continual imitation of God; they will nothing but what he wills; they love nothing but what he loves, they hate nothing but what he hates; ſo that all the truly Juſt may ſay with St. <hi>Paul, That it is God that lives in them, and not they themſelves: that their life is hid in him: and that they have no other ſpirit then his.</hi> So high doth St. <hi>Paul</hi> raiſe the conformity of the Juſt with God, when he ſaith in the eighth chap. to the <hi>Romans, That they are become one ſpirit with him,</hi> which is an evident
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62587:11"/>mark of the higheſt perfection of reſemblance.</p>
               <p>Well then, Brethren! from ſo many reaſons muſt we not in the end conclude, That the Juſt are born of God, and ought not only to be called his children, but are ſo in effect? as ſaith Saint <hi>John</hi> in our Epiſtle, yet it is but one of the conditions for the which the Text that we have taken may be applied fitly to them.</p>
               <p>We muſt ſee, Secondly, whether the other neceſſary conditions are found in them; that is, if they triumph over the world; and if they triumph by faith. This we ſhall ſee in the two parts that remain of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. But before we begin, I crave one moment of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon the firſt. For it is not enough to know who are thoſe whom Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>to be born of God;</hi> but we muſt obſerve, whether we our ſelves be of that number; it is not enough that adoption, or even re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation doth aſſure us of it but we muſt ſeek into the centre of our hearts, and into the moſt ſecret paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of our lives, whether we bare the Image of God; and if we have that reſemblance of holineſs and grace, which doth properly eſtabliſh our right of Filiation: for, whoſoever is unlike his Father is unjuſtly called his ſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they are not only the Philoſophers that will have this reſemblance, and this rapport between the production and its principle, indiſpenſeably neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the eſſence of their relation; neither are they the modern Divines that introduce this neceſſity. Have not the moſt ancient Fathers been of this opinion? Judge ye of it by this fine learned expreſſion of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzen,</hi> who ſays, <hi>the Son is the definition of the Father,</hi> that is, the Son is but the expounding of what his Father is: ſo, the reſemblance between the Father and the Son is no leſs indiſpenſeable, then between the definition of a thing, and the thing defined it ſelf: which another <hi>Gregory</hi> hath more clearly expreſſed, when he called the Son the Image of the Father. But what need is there of reaſons and Authorities, to prove to you the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62587:11"/>neceſſity of this reſemblance, ſince Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Saint <hi>John,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> aſſure us of it; when they tell us, that a man is the childe only of him, whoſe works he does?</p>
               <p>It is then, a truth out of queſtion, That we are not the children of God, but ſo far as we reſemble him; by imitation of his vertue, and by this conformity of our life and innocence with his.</p>
               <p>By this principle, it is eaſie to diſcern whether we are born of God, and it is impoſſible to be deceived upon ſo certain a rule; It is the ſame that our Apoſtle gives us in the ſecond chapter of his firſt Epiſtle, <hi>If you know,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that God is juſt, know that whoſoever doth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is born of him.</hi> But, becauſe this rule may poſſibly be too vaſt, and ſome deſpair is to be feared, if, to be the children of God we muſt be like him in all the excellencies of his holineſs; and in the great number of vertues comprehended in his Juſtice, the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the ſame Epiſtle, reduceth the neceſſity of this reſemblance to the love of our Neighbour; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let us love one another, for love is of God, and whoſoever loveth is born of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> how few would be found born of him, though there needed but this one reſemblance to be born of him, ſince, ſo few love their brethren? do you love your brethren, you that tear them by your calumnies? do you love them, you that take pleaſure in their diſgraces? and are tormented with their proſperities? in good earneſt, do you think you love them, who ſeek ſo many occaſions to hurt them, and ſhun all occaſions to help them? no, no! let us not flatter our ſelves, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs ingenuouſly, that we do not love our brethren, while we harbour grudges againſt them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> coldneſs, ſharpneſs, envy, ſuſpition, contempt, with infinite other diſpoſitions and thoughts that are more cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62587:12"/>
               <p> It is not then of us that St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaks in our. Text, becauſe, not loving our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> brethren, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible we ſhould be born of him: the hatred we have for them deſtroying all the reſemblance that (otherwiſe) we ſhould have of him, for what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance can we have of any perſon, if we hate what he loves? ſince love and hate are the two great Movers which carry on the reſt of our Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there is neceſſarily a hatred between two wills, when one hateth what the other loves.</p>
               <p>Will you, then be the children of God? St. <hi>John</hi> hath told you in two words what is neceſſary for that; <hi>Love one another: for whoſoever loveth is born of God.</hi> What! do you refuſe to purchaſe ſo great an honour at ſo cheap a rate? Conſider the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of being children of ſuch a Father, and ſee how eaſily you may obtain it. And that you may have a greater deſire to it, I will ſhew you the illuſtrious victory that they get over the World, who are born of God: it is the ſecond part of my Text, and of my Diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
               <p>Amongſt infinite circumſtances that compoſe an illuſtrious victory,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Clarior laus eſt quo clarior<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> est quem vice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is.</hi> Curt. l. 6.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Non eſt glorioſa victoria niſi ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>int glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i ſa ſa certamina.</hi> Amoroſ. lib. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> Offic.</p>
                  </note> the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable is the force of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie which is overcome, whence a great Hiſtorian took occaſion to ſay, <hi>That a Triumph was ſo much the more illuſtrious, as be was whom we triumph ever:</hi> and <hi>St. Ambroſe</hi> with the ſame ſpirit ſaith, <hi>That no Victory is glorious, but after a difficult combate, and a pertinacious Reſiſtance;</hi> therefore the Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes with ſo much care the powerful Armies of <hi>Pharaoh, Holophernes, Sennacherib,</hi> and all the other
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62587:12"/>great enemies of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> for thereby a greater ground is afforded for admiring the Conqueror; and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the greatneſs of God, the chief cauſe of the victory: even of the Giant whom <hi>David</hi> overcame, the ſacred Hiſtory marks exactly all that might render him terrible; that the triumph of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Shepherd might be ſo much the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, as there was more difficulty to overcome ſo powerful an enemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> muſt follow the Example the Scripture gives me, and let you ſee what is the ſtrength of this world which is overcome in the Text by the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, that you may judge of the glory of the Triumph, and that ſo, I may make you the more deſire it. But firſt, we muſt know what world is here ſpoken of, it being a word very equivocal in Scripture: All the different ſignifications that it makes uſe of may be reduced to two principal, ſince it never ſpeaks of the world but in a phyſical or moral ſenſe, that is, the world is ſtill put in a natural or myſtical ſignification in Scripture.</p>
               <p>Again, the natural world is taken in divers ways: I obſerve three; the firſt is very large, the ſecond leſs, the third leſs then either: for the firſt, by the world the Scripture means ſometimes all the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, both Heaven and Earth; and all that they contain: you have Examples for it in many places, where it ſpeaks of the world as of the work of Creation. Thus <hi>Acts</hi> 17. <hi>verſe</hi> 24. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> makes it evident that he ſpeaks of the created world.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in many Texts it meaneth the Earth only, as in Saint <hi>Matthew chap.</hi> 4. where it is ſaid, <hi>That the Tempter ſhewed Jeſus Chriſt all the Kingdoms of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſometimes in the New Teſtament it ſignifies
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62587:13"/>only men, ſo it is expounded in many places of the Goſpel, and in the Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and Saint <hi>John:</hi> as, when it is ſaid in the ſecond of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians chap.</hi> 5. <hi>verſe</hi> 19. <hi>That God was in Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling the World to himſelf.</hi> You ſee that there the World ſignifies only men.</p>
               <p>To take it then phyſically, that is, in a natural ſenſe. The world in Scripture means always one of theſe three things, either the whole Univerſe, or the Earth, or Mankind.</p>
               <p>But, to take it ſpiritually, in a moral or myſtical ſenſe, it ſometimes ſignifies, according to the ſtyle of Scripture, thoſe who ſeek only earthly things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out caring to obtain the heavenly, as <hi>John</hi> 16.20. where Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to his Apoſtles, <hi>You ſhall weep,</hi> but the world ſhall rejoyce again in this ſpiritual way; it ſignifies all the corrupt principles that men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly follow in their converſation; in which ſenſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> chap. 6. <hi>that the World was crucified unto him, and he unto the World.</hi> I doubt not but it is in this ſenſe, that we muſt take the world in our Text, becauſe in Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Language, throughout this Epiſtle; we muſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine by the world a certain ſpirit of pleaſure, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and ambition that reigns amongſt men; he explains it enough in the ſecond <hi>Chap. verſe</hi> 16. <hi>All that is in the World, is the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the Eyes, and the pride of life.</hi> And in our Text he makes it appear that this is his meaning, when having ſaid in the verſe before, <hi>The Commandments of God are not grievous.</hi> He gives this reaſon for it, that <hi>thoſe who are born of God overcome the World,</hi> that is, they overcome the things which make the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God grievous; and what are thoſe things, Chriſtians, but the corrupt Maxims we have ſpoken of, Pleaſure, Intereſt, and Ambition.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62587:13"/>
               <p> You ſee then what the World is, judge ye by that how illuſtrious is the victory of thoſe that triumph over it; how great a glory is it to vanquiſh an Enemy ſo ſtrong and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable: the <hi>Caeſars</hi> and the <hi>Alexanders</hi> that heretofore triumph'd over the material World, knew not how to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh this myſtical World, becauſe, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſters of the Univerſe, they were Slaves to their guilty Paſſions, and to the corrupt Maxims of ſin.</p>
               <p>In effect, theſe Maxims, and theſe domineering Paſſions, have got ſo much Authority, and ſo abſolute an Empire over men, that, like a Torrent, it hurries them away, in ſpight of their reaſon, making all reſiſtance vain without the victorious help of Grace. Alas! how many people are there who are very witty, whom Nature has made very ſenſible of Vertue and Honour, who yet ſuffer themſelves to be corrupted by theſe Maxims, and unlucky Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>There are very few of whom Pleaſure hath not made her ſelf Miſtreſs, becauſe the chief Maxim of the World is, to love and ſeek Pleaſure at any rate; this Paſſion hath ſuch Charms, that the braveſt men knew not how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves from it. We have ſeen too much of it in the falls of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> who were both vanquiſh'd by it; and neither the holineſs of the one, nor the wiſdom of the other, could ſave them from it: The example of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and his own confeſſion, does yet more ſenſibly evidence unto us the power of this paſſion; he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, that after all his godly reſolutions to live well, one only word that Pleaſure ſuggeſted to him, plunged him more than ever, in his former diſorderly courſe; Grace was two years continually and ſtrongly labouring to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him; he ſayes himſelf there were continual Combats within him, and after Grace had ſometimes made a good progreſs in the work of his converſion, Pleaſure came and overthrew all; his heart was in the midſt between theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62587:14"/>two Champions; Grace drew it to the one ſide, and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to the other; and when he was ready to yield to Grace, Pleaſure pull'd him by the Cloak, ſaying, What <hi>Auſtin!</hi> Wilt thou forſake this and that? Can'ſt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to forſake me? Can'ſt thou live without my Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements? there needed no more to captivate the heart of <hi>Auſtin;</hi> all that Grace had ſaid, made no more impreſſion on him; and when Grace would yet ſpeak of converſion, he put it off till another time; for Pleaſure held him ſo much her Slave, that he could not, nor would not ſhake off his fetters. O how powerful is this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion! what violent aſſaults it gives! what pertinacious reſiſtances! ſince Grace it ſelf hath ſo much ado to overcome it.</p>
               <p>The Tyrants that perſecuted the Church knew well the force and power that Pleaſure had over the heart of man; for, after they had tryed to corrupt the faith of the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> by the violence of puniſhments; at laſt, they tempted them by the ſweetneſs of pleaſures; and it fell out oft-times, that ſuch as had generouſly reſiſted all the rage and cruelty of the Executioner, ſunk under the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation of Pleaſure. Alas! there were few found generous enough to do that which we read but of one, who being importun'd on all ſides by Pleaſure to yield, bit out his Tongue with his Teeth, and ſpit it in the face of the faireſt Lady of <hi>Rome,</hi> who did ſollicit him; having nothing elſe free to defend himſelf from her, bound as he was, on a Bed ſtrew'd with Roſes: and there were as few of thoſe who were ſo far from yielding to the ſweet perſwaſions of Voluptuouſneſs, that they dyed of ſorrow for living among Pleaſures; as <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory</hi> tells us of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians! we need not wonder that this Paſſion is ſo powerful and formidable an Enemy; flattering that fleſh of ours ſo pleaſingly: the thing we naturally love beſt in the world.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62587:14"/>
               <p> Intereſt and Ambition, which are the two other Enemies that the World preſents us to fight with, have not much leſs force than Pleaſure, to corrupt the innocency of our hearts; and where ſhall we find any almoſt which are not Slaves to the one, or the other of theſe great powers?</p>
               <p>Even in the Times that ſeemed moſt innocent, did not Intereſt make an univerſal Corruption in the World? Was it not the offence of <hi>Saul,</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. where Intereſt had more power than the Commands or Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of God, when his people—victorious over the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekites,</hi> let themſelves be overcome by this ſhameful paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; reſerving in deſpight of God's prohibition, all that was precious in the ſpoyles of the defeated Army? Was it not Intereſt that corrupted a Diſciple in the very Family of Jeſus Chriſt, and tranſported him to that Sacriledge to ſell and betray his good Maſter? Hath not this paſſion daily, the ſame power? Is it not for Intereſt that ſo many in the World continually betray the Son of God? Do not all men almoſt prefer their Intereſt, before his Glory? as St. <hi>Paul</hi> complain'd in his time, <hi>They ſeek their own things, not the things of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Brethren, examine what is done among Chriſtians, ev'n of the beſt Reformed Churches; what fierce deſires have we daily to become richer? and how much coldneſs to become holier and better men? let us conſider what is done at <hi>Rome</hi> upon the Throne of ſplendid Holineſs; you will quickly find, that the ſame paſſion that heretofore made <hi>Judas</hi> ſell Jeſus Chriſt, makes the Pope's Officers ſell the Holy Ghoſt every hour; for they ſell Archbiſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicks. Pardons, and Forgiveneſs of Sins; with the entry into Paradiſe, and many other like Graces, whereof the Holy Ghoſt alone muſt be the Diſtributer, as he is the Principle of the ſame: It is not from the reſentments of an altered man that I ſpeak ſo; within theſe two years there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62587:15"/>have been Experiments enough to make the World ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that of all thoſe that have been converted, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps I am one of the moſt moderate; but I ſpeak that which is to the purpoſe, and which all the World knows. But, though Pleaſure and Intereſt had not ſtrength enough to corrupt our Innocence, Ambition alone would have more then needs for that; it is not impoſſible to find ſome Souls neither voluptuous, nor intereſſed; but I know not where to find any, whom Ambition hath not corrupted: it is that properly, which we may, and ought to call the weak fide of man. He was yet in his ſtate of original In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, above all the aſſaults of Intereſt and Pleaſure; yet at the firſt onſet of Ambition, he let himſelf be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come without reſiſtance; the Devil, who himſelf had proved the force of this temptation, made uſe of no other bait to ſeduce the fair innocent ſouls of <hi>Adam</hi> and his Wife. This Tempter was too crafty not to know, that it was the only part whereby he might take hold of them; and certainly, if there had been a ſtronger temptation, he would not have failed to have made uſe of it in ſuch an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, whereon depended the ſalvation, or total fall of all Mankind.</p>
               <p>Since that unlucky moment, it hath been too much juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that nothing is ſo powerful as Ambition, to make us undertake all things againſt the reſpect and obedience that we owe to God. All Hiſtories, both holy and prophane, are full of examples of this. Was it not that enraged paſſion that made <hi>Abſalom</hi> rebell againſt his father, the beſt father of the World? Was it not the ſame paſſion that made <hi>Athalia</hi> the Murdereſs of her own Children, after the death of <hi>Ochoſias</hi> her Husband, the tenderneſs of a Mother being incapable to take away her ambition to be a Sovereign; was not the ambition of another woman cruel, when, going to take poſſeſſion of the Throne, ſhe made her Coach and Horſes to go over the body of her father
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62587:15"/>that was newly ſlain? here is too much, my Brethren, to manifeſt the power of this inhumane paſſion, ſince it choaks the tendereſt and ſtrongeſt ſentiments of Nature it ſelf: inſomuch, as St. <hi>Baſil</hi> calls it in one of his Letters, <hi>The moſt wicked of all Devils.</hi> Conclude then with me, That the World, which according to St. <hi>John,</hi> and according to our daily Experiments, is nothing but Pleaſure, Intereſt and Ambition, is a very powerful and almoſt invincible Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: and conſequently, if ever we get the Victory over it, it is an infinitely glorious Victory; we muſt fight, before we can overcome ſuch terrible Enemies as theſe; and, if it be true which a Philoſopher ſayes, and <hi>Tertullian</hi> after him, That a man, fighting with the ſame fortune that <hi>Job</hi> had to wreſtle with on his Dunghil, was a ſpectacle, worthy the eyes and attention of God: Is it a leſs worthy ſight, when one man alone fights all the Forces of the World? when he is aſſaulted on all ſides by the moſt tender and charming delights, and yet, the ſweetneſs of thoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures doth not corrupt the integrity of his heart, nor the innocence of his life?</p>
               <p>Chriſtians! what a wonderful ſight is this, to ſee a man ſollicited by the ſtrongeſt temptations of Intereſt, by all the ſplendor of gold and ſilver, and, all the delight of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rich, and his ſoul not caſt down by the violence of this aſſault? In Concluſion, what a Miracle is it, what a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digie, to ſee a man, whom Ambition tempts with the hopes of greatneſs; yet, remaining firm in his humility and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, not dazled with the gliſtering of Thrones, Scepters and Crowns, triumphing thus over the World, and all its glory! O how well may the Apoſtles, and all the juſt, who have thus triumphed, ſay with St. <hi>Paul, We are the ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God, of Angels, and of men.</hi> Spectacles of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance in reſpect of God, of admiration in reſpect of Angels, and of aſtoniſhment in reſpect of men.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62587:16"/>
               <p> O what a glorious Triumph is obtained by them that are born of God, ſince they are Conquerors of a World ſo difficult to be overcome! we muſt not doubt, but that thoſe who are born of God, have, in effect, got this Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſince the World we ſpeak of, that is, Pleaſure, Intereſt and Ambition, can get no advantage, with all his Forces, over thoſe that have the honour to reſemble God, as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren reſemble their father: and, this Adoption that he hath made of them, being a ſpiritual generation, we muſt not doubt, but that he doth impart his Spirit unto them: becauſe, it is according to the Spirit that they are his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and that, being filled with his divine Spirit, it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie for them to triumph over all that is contrary to its Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims, and the purity of its Sentiments.</p>
               <p>This is it which made our Apoſtle ſay immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Text, That <hi>the Commandments of God were not grievous,</hi> to them that were born of him, as he explains himſelf ſoon after; for in truth what Commandment did God ever make, whereunto the obedience is not eaſie to any that is become holy in ſome ſort, like him, by this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Regeneration, and by this communication of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? what difficulty will they find to obey him, when they are Maſters, and victorious of all that hinders their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him? our Pleaſure, our Intereſt, and our Ambition being (as they are) the greateſt obſtacles of our fidelity to his commands, no doubt; but when we have overcome theſe three powerful Enemies of the Law of God, all the obedience that lieth upon us proves eaſie to us; for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, all the pains we find in doing Gods Will, is, that Pleaſure, Intereſt, or Ambition perſwades us to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: but, when we have triumphed over theſe three paſſions, which are properly that which St <hi>Paul</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12.) calleth, <hi>The Spirit of the World;</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> in our Text, <hi>the World</hi> it ſelf; then, whatever God commands is ſo far from painful, that we find pleaſure in it: and the reaſon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62587:16"/>of this reliſh, and this eaſineſs, is no other, but what we ſay, as our Apoſtle doth ſo evidently juſtifie, when, after he had ſaid, <hi>The Commandments of God are eaſie;</hi> he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently brings the proof, <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all that is born of God, overcometh the World;</hi> letting us ſee manifeſtly, that there is nothing but the World, that is, its Spirit, and its Maxims, that makes our obedience uneaſie; and, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible mark of overcoming the World, is, the eaſineſs we find in obeying the Commandments of God.</p>
               <p>But alas! how few then are there that have overcome the World, ſince there are ſo few that do not find the Commandments of God grievous? it ſeems to them an inſupportable yoke, even ſo much, that ſometimes they will ſay, that Gods Commandments are of an impoſſible performance.</p>
               <p>You have not then overcome the World, you, who yet complain of their difficulty; who groan under the weight of the yoke, and expreſs ſo much grief to ſubmit your ſelves to the orders and commands that he gives you. No, no, you have not yet triumphed over the World, you that are yet Slaves to your Pleaſures, to your Intereſt, and your Pride; ſince, it is that which is properly call'd the World; this illuſtrious Victory belongs to none but the children of God, whom he hath, as it were, transformed into himſelf, by a reſemblance of holineſs, of ſpirit and life; hope not then for the glory of this triumph, without being firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into this noble Alliance with God: but, as ſoon as you are become his children, by a mending of your courſes, and by a new birth of piety and grace, be you aſſured, that you ſhall triumph over the World, becauſe, the Oracle of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truth hath ſaid it, that, <hi>all which is born of God, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the World:</hi> And ſince it is by Faith that we get this Victory, as the Text tells us, let us examine in the laſt Part of this Diſcourſe, what that Faith is?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62587:17"/>
               <head>The Third Part.</head>
               <p>IT is with the ſpiritual Combats much as with the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral; it doth not ſuffice, in ordinary Combats, to be ſtrong, and to be valiant to overcome; all the World knows, that beſides that, one muſt have Arms, and make uſe of them: Likewiſe, to overcome the World, it is not enough to be born of God,
<note place="margin">Lib. 22. cap. 25. <hi>Victoria de hoc mundo non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris viribus adſcribetur.</hi>
                  </note> we muſt take Arms to oppoſe the violence of this formidable Enemy: for, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith in his Book of the City of God, The victory over the World is not attributed to our Forces, it is not by them we gain it; but, what Arms muſt we make uſe of? nothing can triumph over the World as a principal cauſe, or as an inſtrument of victory which is not born of God; ſince St. <hi>John</hi> doth not attribute this honour, but to thoſe that are ſo born. Our Arms then ought to be ſome of thoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues which they call Theological or Divine; not only, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is the chief object of them, but for that he is their immediate principle, to diſtinguiſh them from other Vertues which they call Moral, that may ſpring from elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Yanta eſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas quae ſi adſit, habentur omnia; ſi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, fruſtra ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur caetera.</hi> Aug.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Then, of neceſſity, it muſt be either Faith, or Hope, or Charity, that muſt ſerve us for Arms in this Combat; but why rather Faith, than the other two? Is not Hope admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably well fitted for this great imployment, ſince it doth promiſe us eternal rewards? there are no temptations, nor aſſaults, that it enableth us not to overcome; or, at leaſt, why ſhould it not be Charity, which is the Queen, and the moſt noble of all vertues, as the Apoſtle aſſures us? and whereof St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes, That having it alone, one hath all; and not having it, it is uſeleſs to have the reſt; which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62587:17"/>he learned of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>That neither Martyrdom, nor the moſt holy things, nor even Faith it ſelf, is any thing without Charity.</hi> Nevertheleſs we muſt believe our Text, which ſaith plainly, <hi>It is by Faith that we overcome the world:</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> agrees well with this ſentiment, when he ſaith, <hi>That it is by Faith that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny juſt perſons have done ſuch wonders;</hi> and that, <hi>They have vanquiſhed Kingdoms</hi> (what Kingdoms, but thoſe of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil?) and that, <hi>They have conquered Eternity:</hi> Is it not of Faith, that our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath ſaid, That nothing ſhall be impoſſible to it; and, that there needs but little of it to work wonders, even to remove Mountains?</p>
               <p>But, whereas there are Chriſtians that have Faith, and in the mean time are rather Slaves of the World, than Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Conquerors of it; what kind of Faith is that, which may be the inſtrument of ſo glorious a victory? It ſeems the Apoſtle, in the <hi>Verſe</hi> that follows the Text, would ſpare us the pains of this ſearch: <hi>Who is he</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that JESUS is the Son of God?</hi> Yet, there being an infinite number of people that believe ſo much, who notwithſtanding, are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther overcome by the World, than Conquerors of it; we are ſtill to ſeek, and have need to repair to Divinity, and to other Texts of Scripture, for the clearing of ſo great, and ſo important a difficulty.</p>
               <p>Divinity diſtinguiſheth two ſorts of Faith, the one dead, the other living. The dead Faith, which is otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unperfect, or unformed, is no more than a conviction we have of a truth upon Divine teſtimony, without any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of our will by that conviction of our underſtanding; ſome call this Faith Speculative, or Hiſtorical, becauſe it makes one believe only the fact of things, without leading him to other Acts, worthy of ſuch a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62587:18"/>
               <p> It was of this Faith that St. <hi>James</hi> ſpake, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.14. when he ſaid, <hi>What can it profit, my Brethren, though a man ſay I have Faith, and hath not Works; Can Faith ſave him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this ſenſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.2. <hi>If I have Faith enough to remove Mountains</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and have not Charity, I am nothing.</hi> There are ſome alſo which call this Faith the Faith of Devils; for an Apoſtle ſpeaking to a man that had Faith without works — <hi>Thou believeſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that there is a God, thou doſt well to believe it; but the Devils believe it too, and therefore they tremble.</hi> The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, for that kind of believing are no leſs Devils, and no leſs wicked.</p>
               <p>This barren Faith is good for nothing, unleſs it be to make us more guilty; ſince, having believed as we ought to believe, we have no excuſe why we have not lived as we ought to live; it is not then this kind of Faith that our Text ſo highly praiſeth, as to ſay, <hi>It is the victory that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the World;</hi> it muſt be a generous and warlike Faith, and not a baſe, cowardly, dejected Faith; which hath no courage neither to undertake, nor to maintain any thing. Scripture and Divinity tell us of another kind of Faith, quite oppoſite; they call it a lively Faith, perfect or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; which, beſides that it at firſt convinceth the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, by the Authorities of revealed Truths; perſwades the will to approve them, by Sentiments conformable to ſuch holy motions; it is what JESUS CHRIST ſaid of St. <hi>John Baptiſt, A burning and a ſhining Lamp:</hi> ſhining, becauſe it brings light and knowledge to the mind; burning, becauſe it brings fire and piety to the heart.</p>
               <p>Of that the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> ſaith, <hi>The juſt ſhall live by Faith;</hi> that is, by reaſon of his Faith; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. and the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaks again of it in the <hi>Chapters</hi> following, and particularly in <hi>Chap</hi> 3.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62587:18"/>
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 28. where he ſaith, <hi>It is the ſenſe of all Chriſtians, that man is justified by Faith, without the works of</hi> Moſes <hi>his Law.</hi> He ſayes as much of it, almoſt in the ſame words, in the beginning of the <hi>fifth Chapter,</hi> and in divers other places of the ſame Epiſtle, and in all his other Epiſtles. St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſayes no leſs of it, when he aſſures the <hi>Gentiles (Acts</hi> 19.) <hi>that God had purified their hearts by Faith:</hi> And in his 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1.8. <hi>You are preſerved</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>by the means of Faith, to be heirs of Salvation;</hi> which is the reward of Faith, as he ſayes preſently after, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. and certainly, it is that which the Apoſtle St. <hi>Jude,</hi> in his Catholique Epiſtle, (<hi>ver.</hi> 20.) calls <hi>moſt holy;</hi> not only, becauſe it is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal holineſs of the Soul, but, becauſe that (as Divines expound it) it fulfilleth all duties of holineſs, by an entire obedience to the Ordinances and Commands of God; which gives occaſion to Divines to call it ſometimes, an <hi>obedient Faith;</hi> and certainly, it is of this Faith that our Text ſpeaketh, when it ſaith, that <hi>the victory that overcometh the World, is Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not therefore enough, Chriſtians, to ſhew you that all that is born of God, overcometh the World, and that it is by Faith it overcometh; it is needful that I tell you moreover, by what Faith: for, we are not without enemies that accuſe us of giving to Faith alone (without joining it with other vertues) this victorious power.</p>
               <p>And indeed, there are too many ſouls among us, either libertine enough, or ill enough inſtructed, to perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that there needs nothing but believing, to overcome all, and to be ſaved: if they had not ſuch thoughts aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we ſhould ſee them live better; for, it is impoſſible to lead ſo ill a life, if they did believe that they muſt lead a better if they will be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Let our Enemies, and our Libertines, and our Ignorants learn then this day, what we think, and what we ought to think of Faith which juſtifies; or, as our Text ſpeaks, which <hi>overcometh the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:62587:19"/>
               <p> The true Sentiment of all Reformed Churches, is, that this Faith is not only a naked and barren belief, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth and confeſſeth only the truth of our myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, without troubling ones ſelf to practiſe that piety which theſe myſteries require: but they all teach us, that this Faith is accompanied with all the holineſs which the Goſpel enjoyns us; ſo that Faith, according to our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is uncapable to juſtifie us, and to overcome the World, if Charity be not with it; and, it is in vain that I believe in JESUS CHRIST, if I love him not, and if I do not that which his Goſpel ordaineth me to do.</p>
               <p>Thus, when we ſay with the Scripture, <hi>That Faith juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, that it cleanſeth the hearts, that it overcometh the World;</hi> we ſpeak not but of a Faith that is loving, patient, humble and holy in all reſpects; it is after this manner that all the Fathers ſpeak of it, and St. <hi>John</hi> himſelf in the Text, as it is evident in the <hi>verſes</hi> that go before, and that follow: For, though he ſaith abſolutely, <hi>That thoſe who believe that JESUS CHRIST is the Son of God, overcome the World;</hi> yet, he ſpeaks before and after, of Charity, and of keeping Gods Commandments, as things inſeparably link<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this victorious Faith. You ſee then, Chriſtians, what that Faith is which overcometh the World, in the juſt; it is that impenetrable Buckler that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of, that beats back all the blows which the Enemy aims at us: A man armed with this Faith, may ſay with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>That what temptation ſoever he ſhall endure, no aſſaults ſhall ſeparate him from the love of JESUS CHRIST:</hi> Nothing ſhall debauch him from his duty, nothing ſhall make him the ſlave of ſin; let the World come with all its Forces, with all the ſweets of Pleaſure, with all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of Intereſt, with all the pom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Ambition; it will make but vain Enterpriſes, unſucceſsful Aſſaults upon a man, armed with this warlike and generous Faith: for,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62587:19"/>what can pleaſure ſay to him able to corrupt him? if ſhe promiſeth to his body all ſhe hath of tender and ſweet, what will the Juſt do in this rough aſſault, where he hath all pleaſures to fight againſt? He will oppoſe his Faith. I believe in that God, will he ſay, who would not live but in pennance, while he lived amongſt us, alwayes ſevere to his fleſh, alwayes mortified in his mind; never in pleaſure, and almoſt continually in grief: who found in the bitterneſs of his death, nothing but Gall and Vinegar to ſweeten it. What! ſhall I believe theſe things, and in the mean time, abandon my ſelf to thoſe guilty pleaſures? No, I will not.</p>
               <p>The aſſaults of Intereſt need no leſs reſolution and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, they ſollicit the faithful Soul with all the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that Gold and Silver are able to make in this World; being preſſed by this aſſault, what doth he? He takes his ordinary ſhield, he oppoſeth his Faith. O! (ſaith he) I believe, that God made himſelf poor, to make me rich; that he would not poſſeſs any thing on earth; that at his birth he had nothing but ſtraw to lie upon; that during his life, he had nothing whereon to lay his head; that at his death, he was naked: And, ſhall I, to make my ſelf rich, do this injuſtice? ſhall I, ſuffer my ſelf to be corrupted by my Intereſt? No, I will not.</p>
               <p>Neither ſhall Ambition have any more advantage over the faithful Soul, how violently ſoever it aſſaults him. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I ſee Ambition with her gliſtering and her pomps, tempting the heart of the Juſt, flattering him with all her ſplendor and grandeur, which uſe to dazle others; what will he do in this aſſault? that, which he did in the former; He will take Faith, and oppoſe it againſt this Enemy that preſſeth him: What! (ſaith he) that God, in whom I believe, who abaſed himſelf ſo far, as to become man; did humble himſelf to the meaneſt things, ev'n to death; to the moſt ſhameful and infamous death: And, ſhall I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62587:20"/>my ſelf by the diminution of his glory? ſhall I drive on my fortune, as far as vanity will entice me? No, I will not; it ſhall never be ſaid, that my life hath bely'd my Faith. I believe there are eternal Rewards to crown all my fidelity, if I ſink not under theſe Temptations that the World leads me in o: I believe there are everlaſting pains to puniſh my baſeneſs, if I do ſink under them: What then! ſhould I be ſo far out of my wits, and beſides my ſenſes, as to reſolve to do it? No, the World muſt ſtay, till I believe theſe things no more. Thus it is, Brethren, that Faith ſpeaks, thus it is that ſhe fights, thus it is that ſhe triumphs, when ſhe is right: when Faith is, as it ought to be, animated with the Spirit of all vertues; and, when we are ſatisfied by the effects, that we have this Faith. We have it not, Chriſtians, when we yield ſo eaſily to the firſt ſollicitations of Pleaſure, of Intereſt, and of Ambition: Alas! how can your Faith be victorious over the World, while you are ſtill Slaves to Paſſion, which is the World it ſelf? and whil'ſt you obſerve the Laws and Maxims of the World, more religiouſly than thoſe of God.</p>
               <p>The Faith that is victorious over the World, confeſſeth JESUS CHRIST on all occaſions, loves him at all times, and ſerves and follows him through all things; in good earneſt, Chriſtians, do you do ſo? Alas! how ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily may it be ſeen, with never ſo little reflection on our ſelves, that we have not this Faith? ſince within us, all is full of Revolts, Ingratitudes, and Infidelities towards CHRIST, whom we crucifie and defame daily, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> reproacheth in the <hi>ſixth</hi> of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews.</hi> Is that believing in JESUS Chriſt with a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Faith, when we believe in him to crucifie him, and diſgrace him, by the diſorders of our ſhameful lives? Take my Brethren, take other courſes more worthy of him, and of your ſelves; live conformably to the belief of his Goſpel, let his love and his will reign in your hearts, as well
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62587:20"/>as his Truths in your minds: in a word, let your works and your life be ſutable to the holineſs of your Faith, and then you will have a victorious Faith, and you ſhall be in the number of the juſt ones, of whom St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith in our Text, <hi>That they are born of God, that they triumph over the World, and that they triumph by Faith.</hi> God give you that Grace in this life, that he may crown you in the next with GLORY.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Unto this Great GOD, Immortal, Inviſible, Adorable FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER, SON, and HOLY GHOST, who gives us theſe glorious Hopes, be Honour, Bleſſing, and Eternal Magnificence.</hi> AMEN.</p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
